<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A godlye and fruitefull sermon against idolatrie vvherein the foolishe distinctions and false interpretations of the seconde commandement, and other scriptures pretended by the Papists, are plainly and fully confuted: preached the .xv. daye of Ianuarie. 1581. in the parrishe church of Eaton Sooken, within the countie of Bedforde, by P.W. minister and preacher in that place.</title>
            <author>White, Peter, Vicar of Eaton Socon.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1581</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15104</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25402</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106308</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842026</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842026</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6649</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15104)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6649)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 719:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A godlye and fruitefull sermon against idolatrie vvherein the foolishe distinctions and false interpretations of the seconde commandement, and other scriptures pretended by the Papists, are plainly and fully confuted: preached the .xv. daye of Ianuarie. 1581. in the parrishe church of Eaton Sooken, within the countie of Bedforde, by P.W. minister and preacher in that place.</title>
                  <author>White, Peter, Vicar of Eaton Socon.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[44] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Frauncis Coldocke,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1581.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>P.W. = Peter White.</note>
                  <note>Imprint varies: "by" (Folger Shakespeare Library copy) or "for" (Harvard University. Library copy) F. Coldocke--STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B-C D² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6649:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6649:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6649:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6649:2"/>
            <p>A Godlye and fruitefull Sermon againſt Idolatrie: VVherein the fooliſhe diſtinctions and falſe interpretations of the ſeconde com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, and other ſcriptures preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Papiſts, are plainly and fully confuted: Preached the .xv. daye of Ianuarie. 1581. in the Parriſhe Church of <hi>Eaton Sooken,</hi> within the <hi>Countie of</hi> Bedforde, <hi>by</hi> P. W. <hi>Miniſter and Preacher in that place.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Tertullian.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Jdolum tam fieri, quam coli, Deus prohibet.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Lactantius.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Non est dubium quin religio nulla ſit, vbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſimulachrum est.</p>
            </q>
            <p>AT LONDON <hi>Imprinted by</hi> Frauncis Coldocke. 1581.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:6649:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6649:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>VCHE HATH been the raſh and vndiſcreet deling of the defendours of the Popiſhe er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours and abuſes, reprooued in this little treatiſe, that after the preaching of this Sermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, diuers ſlanderous reports were giuen forth of me: whereby I am enforced in the defence of my Miniſtery, to bring to the view of many, that thing which at the firſte I deliuered to a fewe, rather yeelding my ſelfe vnto the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of euery indifferent reader, then to hazard wyth ſilence the credit of my function to the mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes of ſlanderous reporters. And herein I am to deſire the reader to beare with me, for that I haue not ſo ſtrictly folowed my text in this place, as the nature of reading &amp; preaching requireth: but taking
<pb facs="tcp:6649:4"/> occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therof to enter the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of a common place, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber (I pray you) that extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry occaſion did leade (yea rather drawe) me thervnto. For where I had begun to read and interprete the reuelation of <hi>S. John,</hi> and had in my laſt Lecture handled ſome part of this Text here recited, by reaſon of a contention begun a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs, about a remnaunt of a Roodelofte, then ſtanding in the Churche where this Sermon vvas preached, (which Roodelofte in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed wanteth nothing of his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſtate, but only the images and vppermoſt front. The loft being nine foote in bredth yet ſtandeth, with the beame where the Roode or Idoll did ſtande, hauing the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacles that ſometimes ſtoode vpon the Alters placed from the beame aforeſayde, downewarde vnto the loft for a Diuiſion, and all the neither front downeward, remaining as it did In the time of
<pb facs="tcp:6649:4"/> popery.) A monument with ſmall charge and leſſe laboure, quicklye repayred for the idolatrie that it was firſte appointed vnto. Vpon this occaſion (I ſay) after a ſhorte recitall of thinges touched in my lecture laſt before, I tooke matter of the Candleſticks mencioned in the Text to handle the Queſtion then in contention among vs, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the ſame at large as I haue layde it foorth to the view of all that ſhall reade it. Wherein I haue neither (as I thinke) ſhewed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, raſhneſſe, or yet plaid the part of a mad man, (as it hath pleaſed ſome to report of me) but ſimply and truelye, to the conuincing of popiſh errors and idolatrie, and to the quieting and ſtrengthning of the weake conſciences of the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of mine owne charge, layed foorth the truth for ſome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of my dutie and function in this behalfe. But ſuch is the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficultie of the reedifying &amp; buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="tcp:6649:5"/> vp of the Lordes houſe, as well appeareth both by the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the materiall Temple, in the dayes of <hi>Zorobabell, Ioſedech, Nehemias,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Eſdra. 4. Agg. 1. Nehem. 4. Ioh. 2.</note> and <hi>Eſdras,</hi> where not only the forraine enemies but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo counterfeite <hi>Iſraëlites,</hi> did ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbe and hinder the Builders, that in fortie and ſixe yeares, they with much difficultie did hardlye finiſh the ſame. And the building of the ſpirituall houſe or Temple of the Lorde, but cheefely now in theſe euill, laſt, and daungerous dayes, wherein the Deuil and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt rageth extremely (becauſe their time is but ſhorte) yea euen amongſt vs, where the freedom in building of this Houſe vnder a moſt godly and gracious Prince, (whome the Lord euer preſerue) is freelye graunted: by outward e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, as the profeſſed Papiſtes, <hi>Harding, Saunders, Dorman, Heſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins, Allen. &amp;c.</hi> with the rable of <hi>Jebuſites</hi> (no Iheſuits) ſubuerters,
<pb facs="tcp:6649:5"/> no ſauers, doe together with do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſticall enemies, as Atheiſts, Newters, counterfeit Goſpellers, and diſſembling Papiſtes, ſeruing the time, and ſeeking the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of our common Weale, bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily let and hinder this heauenlye building. Wherein they do and will preuaile vntill ſuch time, as al filthie rubbiſh of popiſh religion, be vtterly remoued and caſt forth, as well from the hartes, of all ſuch as builde and are to be builded, as from churches and all other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: which the Lord Ieſus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſpedily accompliſh, that we his people of <hi>Englande,</hi> may be framed an holye and acceptable building vnto him ſelfe, that his glorye maye euer ſhine among vs, and we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuallye preſerued tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the power of the ſame.</p>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:6649:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6649:6"/>
            <head>The Text.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>And I turned me, and ſaw ſeuen golden Candleſticks, and in the middeſt of the ſeuen Candleſticks, one like vnto the ſonne of man.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here heeretofore,</hi> (Derelye beloued) we haue by occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this, learned that Chriſte Ieſus our Sauiour is alwais preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto al thoſe which at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of his voyce turne vnto him, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> figure of this Angel, teſtifying the preſence of Chriſt, ſheweth how vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible a thing it is, to laye foorth and expreſſe the glorye and proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the perſon &amp; office of Chriſt, by an Image made, grauen, and paynted by man, whereby, not onely the madneſſe of the Heathen, that in grauen Images pretended the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation
<pb facs="tcp:6649:7"/> and worſhip of god, but alſo of the Papiſtes, who in their I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magery pretended the like is eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently conuinced.</p>
            <p>It now remaineth, that we examine why in this place the church of God is reſembled or repreſented by Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſticks, &amp; why it may not be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to haue the vſe of Candleſticks, and other ſuch ceremoniall figures, now in the church of God, And this the rather, becauſe in this place, the queſtions of theſe &amp; ſuch like, hath broke in amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vs. For the deciding whereof, the right reuerend &amp; lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned father my L. of L. was deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined this day to haue occupied this place, who being letted w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> weightie matters otherwiſe, cannot now an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere your expectations, wherefore as it ſhall pleaſe God to make me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for the time, I will ſpeake to the conuincing of error, and ſatiſfying the conſciences of the troubled.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that the holye ſpirite of God, may alwayes appeare to bee
<pb facs="tcp:6649:7"/> conſtante and vnuariable, hee vſeth not any one ſimilitude in this reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, or in the whole newe Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but he hath eyther the ſame or the like in the olde, as the figures of Candleſtickes from <hi>Exodus</hi> the xxv. Other cauſes maye bee giuen,<note place="margin">Exod. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> which when the Angels interpeta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall (of theſe Candleſtickes) be handled you ſhall heare.</p>
            <p>Then that it is not only vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, but alſo manifeſtly wicked, to bring ceremoniall fygures and Images into the Churche, becauſe that all ceremoniall fygures at the death of Chriſt were remooued and cleane taken awaye, And to bring them agayn,<note place="margin">Galat.</note> were (as Saint Paule ſayth) to denye Chriſte,<note place="margin">Exod. 20.</note> And ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges by the law and word of god are forbidden.</p>
            <p>But if any do pretend the Cherubs ouer the Ark and the braſen ſerpent to colour Imagery, they do bewray their folly, and lack of vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, for as a perticuler precept doth not
<pb facs="tcp:6649:8"/> diſanul or make fruſtrate a generall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement: but ſerueth or is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied vnto the perticuler or ſpeciall parties &amp; place, for whom &amp; where it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded: ſo theſe Cherubs were not ſeene but only by the hie Prieſt, &amp; that but once by the yeere, and the braſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſerpent was not erected in the Tabernacle or temple, but in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, where the firy ſerpents did bite y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people, which ſerpent <hi>Ezechias</hi> brake al to powder, &amp; caſt it into the brooke <hi>Cedro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> which he would neuer haue done, if there had any vſe at all remayned thereof vnto the people. Therefore theſe thinges be ſo farre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the coulering of imagery in the Church, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they vtterly ouerthrowe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Thus much for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> candleſticks. The queſtion among vs now in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention is of imagery, and whether this part of the Roodelofte yet ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding be a monument of Adolatry or not: whyche queſtion through the paine iangling of ſome raſh and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſkilful perſons are grown into theſe
<pb facs="tcp:6649:8"/> braunches.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt that the Papiſts placed their images in the Churche onely to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent and put menne in memorye and not to bee worſhypped of the people.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> That the ſecond co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandment doth not forbid the making &amp; hauing of images in religion, but the worſhip of them only: for the which there is pretended a tranſlation of <hi>St. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome,</hi> which hath the Text in this maner, <hi>Non facies ſculptile vt adores,</hi> Thau ſhalte not make any grauen image, to the intent to do Godly ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour thereto. There is further pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended <hi>Lactantius de Jmaginibus,</hi> and <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> who ſhould ſay, you ſhal not breake down images wher they may do good as by images <hi>S. Auſtin</hi> thought ſome good might come.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly that <hi>Jdolum</hi> &amp; <hi>Simulachrum</hi> do far differ from that which is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led image or ſimilitude.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this part of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Roodloft yet ſtanding is no monument of ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6649:9"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> That the defendors of theſe abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities (whoſe opinion &amp; iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to the diſcredit of the doctrine of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel in this place was &amp; is take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollo his oracles, in ſo much as ſome here preſent haue ſayd, that they had rather haue their learning, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended theſe thinges, then much ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: &amp; many of you haue ſayde, that they be wel read in ſcriptures &amp; doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, they haue the ſcriptures &amp; fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers at their fingers ends, ſo redye are they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our miniſter is not able to anſwere them. That y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> defendors I ſay haue neither learning, reaſon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nor gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues. It ſhal appeare in handling of theſe things both by ſcripture doctors, and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, as occaſion offereth.</p>
            <p>Now touching the firſt branche, It ſhall playnely appeare that the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes both by decrees of Counſels, writings of their Doctors &amp; practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, had Images in their Churches not only to repreſent, but eſpecially to be worſhipped. In the <hi>2.</hi> councell
<pb facs="tcp:6649:9"/> of <hi>Nice</hi> it was thus decreede, <hi>Defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimus enim omni diligentia et cura, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerandas &amp; ſanctas imagines ad mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum et formam venerande et viuifica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis crucis coloribus et teſſellis aut alia quauis materia commodé paratas dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candas et in templis ſanctis Dei collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candas habendaſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>. <hi>We doe with all care &amp; dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce decree that holy I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages worthy of worſhip be made after the manner &amp; faſhion of the worſhipful &amp; holy Croſſe that gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth life, with colours &amp; wainſcot or any other matter conueniently prepared be placed &amp; had in the holy temples of god,</hi>
               </hi> And in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Concil Nic 2. An. 681 temp Adriani primi Pope act. 10.</note> 
               <hi>Imaginis enim honor in</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>reſultat, et qui adorat imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, in ea adorat quodcun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> deſcriptu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> argumentum, <hi>Truly the honor done vnto the image reboundeth vnto that thing that the image doeth repreſente, and hee that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippeth an image worſhippeth in the image, vvhatſoeuer is by the image repreſented.</hi>
               </hi> And ymmedyatelye after, in the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:6649:10"/> ſeſſion,<note place="margin">Jbidem.</note> 
               <hi>Sancta ſynodus exclamauit, omnes ſic credimus, omnes idem ſapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, omnes approbantes ſubſcripſimus, haec est fides Apoſtolorum, haec est fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des patrum, haec eſt fides orthodoxoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, haec fides orbem terrarum confirmauit, credentes in vnum Deum in trinitat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> laudatum venerandas imagines am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexamur, qui ſecus agunt Anathemate percelluntur, qui ſic non ſentiunt ab ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia depelluntur. <hi>The holy Synode cried out a main, we al do thus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, we all ſo think, we all allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame haue ſubſcribed, this is the faith of the Apoſtles, this is the faith of the fathers, this is the faith of all them that taught the truth, this fayth hath confyrmed the whole world, we beleeuing in one God praiſed in trinitie do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue and imbrace Images to be worſhipped, whoſoeuer do not ſo, be excommunicated, whoſoeuer thinketh otherwiſe, let him be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled out of the Church.</hi>
               </hi> The fourth councell of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:6649:10"/> holden in the time of Pope <hi>Adrian</hi> the ſecond hath thus decreede, <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> imaginem domini noſtri Ieſu Chriſti et omnium ſaluatoris equo honore cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> libro ſanctorum Euangeliorum adorari de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerminꝰ, <hi>We do decree, that the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly image of our Lord Ieſu Chriſte the Sauior of al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 8. Cap. 3.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall be adored and worſhipped with equall ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the bookes of the holy E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſts.</hi> And in the ende of the ſame Canon, <hi>Dignius eſt enim prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter congruentia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rationis, et antiquiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam traditionem, propter honorem qui ad principalia ipſa refertur, et iam de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claratiue imagines honorentur et ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentur, <hi>It is very meet both for the congruence of reaſon, &amp; the moſt ancient tradition, and for the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor that is referred vnto the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal that images be honored and worſhipped,</hi> And in the councell of <hi>Trident</hi> the laſt ſeſſion, <hi>uſdem E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopis mandat, vt doceant ſanctorum inuocationem, reliquiorum honorem, et imaginu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vſum, et eos qui aliter doceant
<pb facs="tcp:6649:11"/> impié ſentire, praedicent, id quod conſili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> praeſertim verô ſecundae Niciae de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretis contra imaginum oppugnatores est ſancsitum.</hi> The Synode co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Biſhops, that they teache the inuocation of Saintes, the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of reliques, the vſe of images and they ſhall preach that all that teach otherwiſe, are of a wicked iudgement, the which thing is ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in the decrees of Counſels but eſpecially in the ſecond coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of Nice againſt the oppugnors or gainſaiers of images.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rationale du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randi lib. 3. de pict. et or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namentis Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſie.</note> And doctor <hi>Durandus</hi> amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g other things for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worſhip of images, hath this verſe: <hi>Effigiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſti qui tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſis pronus adora, <hi>Thou that paſſeſt by the Image of Chriſt, fall downe groueling and worſhip:</hi>
               </hi> And a little after, <hi>Picturas non licet frangere ea occaſione quod ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orari non debent, pictura nam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur plus mouere animum qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra. <hi>It is not lawful to breake ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges becauſe they ſhoulde not be worſhipped for it is thought an
<pb facs="tcp:6649:11"/> Image doeth more moue the mynd then Scripture.</hi>
               </hi> Thus you heare that imagery was placed in the Church of Papiſtes to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped, whereby you may well per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, how litle learning they haue, that among you ſo ſtoutly and bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affirme the contrary, yea, theyr knowledge is little worth, no not in Popery.</p>
            <p>To the ſecond branch of this queſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,<note place="margin">The ſecond braunche.</note> I ſay it is euident vnto al men that are not wilfully blinded that the ſecond commaundement doth as ſharpely forbidde the making and hauing of images in religion, as the worſhippe of them: The commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement ſtandeth of three braunches, The firſte forbyddeth the makyng of Images in relygion: For the Lorde in the firſt table doeth onely reſpecte his owne worſhippe, and thynges belonging vnto hys wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyppe and Relygyon: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all vayne ianglynge of ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelynge Papyſtes, that drawe
<pb facs="tcp:6649:12"/> the vſe of ſtamping, printing, gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, caruing, or paynting, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane or ciuile ends, is vtterly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued from the meaning and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of this commaundement, and can therefore haue no place in this queſtion. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond braunch forbiddeth the worſhipping of ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third braunch conteineth a ſharpe threatning of almightie God againſt ſuch as ſhall for religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſake either make or worſhip an image. For the firſt braunch of the ſecond co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement theſe are the words:<note place="margin">Exod. 2.4.</note> 
               <hi>Non facies tihi ſcuptile, nec vl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam ſimilitudinem eorum quae ſunt in coelo. &amp;c. <hi>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelfe any grauen image, nor any likenes of any thing that is in heauen. &amp;c.</hi>
               </hi> Of the ſecond braunch theſe are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> words, yea after S. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome, <hi>Non adorabis neque coles ea, <hi>Thou ſhalt neither bowe thy ſelfe vnto them, nor before them, nor worſhip them.</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 4.</note> And thus doth <hi>Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fourth of <hi>Deutronomy</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprete
<pb facs="tcp:6649:12"/> the commandment, ſaying<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Take heede vnto your ſelues dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently, for you ſaw no Image, nor likenes of any thing at the time or day when the Lorde ſpake with you in <hi>Horeb</hi> in the midſte of the fyre,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 4. ver. 15.16.17.18.19.</note> 
               <hi>leaſt happilye you corrupte your wayes, and make vnto your ſelues any grauen image or like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of anye thing. &amp;c.</hi> Loe here not only the Worſhip, but the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king is forbidden, and the making of Images is here called the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting of their wayes. <hi>Eſayas</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Hierome</hi> his tranſlation <hi>Plaſtoe idoli omnes nihil ſunt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 44.</note> 
               <hi>All the makers of Images are of no reputacion,</hi> yea not only the Image, but the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage maker is accurſed. The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Dauid</hi> after <hi>Hierome</hi> his tranſlation ſaith,<note place="margin">Pſal. 113.134.</note> 
               <hi>Similis ſunt ijs om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes qui ea faciunt, <hi>They are all like vnto Images that make Images,</hi> And <hi>Tertullian</hi> that is pretended for Images, ſayeth: <hi>Jdolum tam
<pb facs="tcp:6649:13"/> fieri quam coli Deus prohibet,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Libro de. Idolat.</note> 
                  <hi>God doth forbid as well the making and the worſhipping of images. <hi>Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tò precedit vt fiat qùod coli poſſit, can<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> prius ne fiat ſi coli non licet, propter hanc cauſam ad eradicandam, ſcilicet materiam idolatriae lex diuina pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamat ne fecerit is idolum, et coniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gens ne<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ſimilitudinem eorum &amp;c.</hi> By how much the making of an Image goeth before the worſhip: euen ſo much muſt the making be firſt auoyded if it may not bee worſhipped, therefore to the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter pulling vp of the matter of Idolatry, the lawe of god pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimeth that you make no image and ioyneth heereto, nor anye ſimilitude of thynges in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. &amp;c.</hi>
               </hi> And <hi>Lactantius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. R. de origine erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris. cap. 19.</note> 
               <hi>Non est dubium quin religio nulla ſit vbicun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Simulachrum est, Nam ſi Religio ex diuinis rebus est, Diuini au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem nihil est niſi in Coeleſtibus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, carent Religione Simulachr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>:
<pb facs="tcp:6649:13"/> 
                  <hi>There is no doubte, that there is no religion whereſoeuer there is any imagery, for if religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be in diuine thinges, and nothing is deuine, but that is in Heauenlye thinges, then is imagery voide of all religion.</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Concil. Eliber. Anno dom. 300.</note> The councell of <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertine</hi> holden in <hi>Spayne</hi> Anno three hundred, thus decreede agaynſt I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, <hi>Placuit picturas in Eccleſià eſſe non debere, ne quod colitur et ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratur in parietibus depingatur. <hi>It is decreed that pictures oughte not to be in the church, nor that which is honoured and worſhipped bee paynted or ſtained vppon Walls.</hi>
               </hi> And Saynt <hi>Auguſtine</hi> iudged that <hi>Marcus Varro</hi> the <hi>Romane</hi> came ſo muche nearer vnto Religion,<note place="margin">Auguſt. de Ciuitate Dei.</note> by howe muche hee abhorred I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magerye in Religion. The Law of Nature did teache <hi>Varro,</hi> that God being inuiſible, and withall incomprehenſible, coulde in no wife be repreſented by thinges viſible, &amp; thinges made by the ſkill of man of
<pb facs="tcp:6649:14"/> the ſame iudgement was <hi>Iuuenall</hi> and diuers others, <hi>Dicite pontifices</hi> (ſayth <hi>Iuuenall) <hi>in ſacro quid facit Aurum:</hi> Tell me ye Prieſts what profiteth your golden Images in Religion:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lactan. lib. 2. de origine er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roris. 2.</note> In like maner <hi>Perſian</hi> &amp; <hi>Horace,</hi> who in deriding imagery are brought in by <hi>Lactantius</hi> and <hi>S. <hi>Ierome.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>O curas hominum, ô quantum eſt in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus inane,</l>
               <l>O curue in terras omniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, et coelestium inanes.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Oh the cares of men, how void of the vnderſtanding of thinges hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly, oh how groueling vpon the earth doe they vainely bend their cogitations.</hi> And <hi>Horace,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Olim truncus eram ſiculnus inutile lig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, cum faber incertus ſcannum fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceret ne Priapum, maluit eſse Deum, Deus inde ego furum at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> auium, max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ima formido. <hi>Yerewhile I was a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted wilde figge Tree, both barren and vnprofitable, when the workeman was in doubt whether
<pb facs="tcp:6649:14"/> he would make me a forme, a tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, or (his God)</hi> Priapus, <hi>in the ende hee woulde haue mee a god, from this parentage I am become a god, a terrible ſcarecrowe to theeues and crowes,</hi>
               </hi> Thus wee heare by ſcripture and fathers that the ſecond commaundement doth as well forbid the making of Images as the worſhip of them, and Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, Councels, yea &amp; heathen men, alſo condemne the hauing of them in religion. The learning therefore reading and wiſedome of thoſe that with all boldneſſe ſay the contrary, ye ſee is nothing, and in theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters is as little worth, but you may ſee in them the common Prouerbe verified, None is ſo bolde as blinde Bayard that ſeeth nothing, Thus much for the ſecond Branche of the Queſtion.</p>
            <p>That the places of Scripture re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouing the Idolatrie of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then are not to be applied vnto the Images of Chriſtians, and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene
<pb facs="tcp:6649:15"/> 
               <hi>idolum ſimulachrum</hi> and <hi>imaginem,</hi> is greate dyfference, whereto was aleaged Saint <hi>Paule, <hi>Non est Idolum in Mundo,</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.</note> 
               <hi>There is not an Image in the world.</hi> Alſo S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> was aleaged to the ſame purpoſe. This dyſtinction (I ſay) is lewd, wicked, and Popyſhe firſt it is lewd and wicked, becauſe it is dyrectly agaynſt the worde of God, and the practiſe of the true Churche of God, and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtrueth the meaning of Saint <hi>Paule</hi> and falſifieth bothe the wordes and meaning of Saynte <hi>Augustine</hi> (as you ſhall heare.)</p>
            <p>For betweene the Iewe and the Chryſtyan in ſubſtaunce of Relygion, there is no difference, they bothe haue the ſelfe and the ſame GOD and Saluation in Chryſte Ieſus as appeareth by <hi>Adam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen.</note> 
               <hi>Iſaac, Iacob,</hi> and all others. Therefore Chryſte ſayde vnto the Iewes <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> was gladde to ſee my daies,
<pb facs="tcp:6649:15"/> hee ſawe it, and reioyced. And Saynte <hi>Paule</hi> bryngeth the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lygion of Chryſte from the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſes made to <hi>Abraham.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Galat. 4.</note> And to the Hebrewes, hee ioyneth the Iewe and the Chriſtyan togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in one promyſe and felow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyppe in Chryſte,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.</note> Chriſte being as ſaith S <hi>Peter,</hi> the Corner ſtone. <hi>Irenaeus</hi> alſo witneſſeth the ſame in theſe words: <hi>Siue d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bitatione igitur &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pet. act. 2.</note> Therefore w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out all doubt or gainſaying, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtle witneſſing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, there is one &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſelfe ſame god which iudged thoſe things (of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes) and ſifteth out the thinges (of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chriſtians) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> now are. Thys alſo affyrmeth <hi>Origen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Origen hom. en Eſay. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Euſebius</hi> alſo, &amp; <hi>Auguſtine</hi> agree in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. In outward things in deede as Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lityque gouernment, Ceremonyes,<note place="margin">Euſ. hiſt. eccl. lib. 1.</note> Ceremonyal Lawes, and the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward partes of the Sacrament,<note place="margin">Aug. ſup. Ioh. hom. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> there is greate dyfference, but in ſignification, grace, ſubſtance of Religyon, Morrall preceptes,
<pb facs="tcp:6649:16"/> and commaundeth, there is no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, otherwiſe Chriſt Ieſus, S. <hi>Paule,</hi> and the other Apoſtles, had expounded and applied them vnto Chriſtians in vayne, then there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no difference in theſe reſpectes, betweene the Iewes &amp; Chriſtians, when we ſee the Appoſtles apply the name Idole, and the hauing or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Images, with the deteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as well vnto the Iew as vnto the Gentile,<note place="margin">Ier. 2.</note> we maye well ſee and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue that the like application be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth vnto vs. This ſhall you ſee in <hi>Ieremy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezech. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Ezechiell, Eſay,</hi> and <hi>S, <hi>Paule,</hi>
               </hi> and many other places: It is lewde and wicked therefore to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye the application of the ſcripture by condemning the Idolatrie of the Iew and Gentiles vnto or agaynſte the imagery of Chriſtians in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.<note place="margin">Rom. 1. 2. Cor. 6.</note> Now concerning the abuſing of theſe wordes of <hi>S. <hi>Paule,</hi> Scimus quod idolum nihil eſt in mundo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 8.2.</note> 
               <hi>Wee know that an Idole or Image is nothing in the World,</hi> Whereby
<pb facs="tcp:6649:16"/> he denieth not the being of Idoles, or Images in ſubſtance and fourm, but in vſe, qualitie, and power,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 8. ver. 4.5:</note> and thereto hee addeth, and that there is no other GOD but one, for although there bee that are called Gods in Heauen and in earth, (as there bee manye Gods, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye Lordes) yet vnto vs is oure GOD the Father, of whome are all thinges, and wee in him, And our Lorde Ieſus Chriſte, by whome are all thinges, and wee by him.<note place="margin">Eſay. 44. Rom. 1.</note> The Gentiles and Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters, pretended the repreſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of GOD, who is incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible, by an Image made by man, which cannot be, and therefore to this ende or vſe there is no Idole or Image, they alſo pretended by theyr Imagerye manye and dyuerſe Goddes, whiche is alſo falſe, and is not as Saynt <hi>Paule</hi> ſayth.</p>
            <p>They alſo pretended power vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theyre Idoles, and that the
<pb facs="tcp:6649:17"/> thinges offered in the preſence of their Images were ſanctiſed and dedicated vnto GOD, whiche is alſo falſe, for Saynte Paule ſayth, Suche Offeringes are the Offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringes and Cuppe of Deuils, and thus you maye ſee, Saynte Paule denyeth not the being and forme of Idoles, but the vſe, qualitye, and power vnto them aſcrybed by menne, and vſing the wordes of <hi>Eſaye,</hi> who ſayeth: an Idole or Image is nothing: it is vayn, and vanitie it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 44. Habac. 3.</note>
               <hi>Habacuc</hi> ſayeth: They are <hi>Mendacia, <hi>Leaſinges.</hi>
               </hi> Thus yee alſo ſee, that the abuſing of theſe wordes of Saynte Paule, is as lewde and wicked. And where Saynte <hi>Auguſtine</hi> is pretended to allowe of Images, and the Matter of them to ſtande where they maye doe ſome good,<note place="margin">De verb. dom ſup. Math, Serm. 6.</note> (as though this Father thoughte they mighte doe good) heere is the Booke from whence that was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended,
<pb facs="tcp:6649:17"/> the place is cleane contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye. In his Sermon vppon the eyghth of <hi>Mathewe,</hi> hee greatelye enueigheth agaynſte Idoles, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they call vs, the Enimyes of theyre Idoles, ſo God graunte and bring them into our power that they maye be broken as the reſte are, but this I warne you, when they are not in your iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, you doe it not: for it is the propertie of euill menne and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Circumcillions, where they haue no iuriſdiction to aduenture vppon them, and deſyre theyr owne Death, they make vnprofytable haſte. You all that were late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye preſente, hearde what was reade, When the Lande is gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen you in poſſeſſyon: Fyrſte hee ſayeth in poſſeſſyon, and then hee telleth what you ſhall doe: You ſhall breake downe theyre Alters, hewe downe their Groues, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowe theyre Monumentes, when you haue authoritie, this
<pb facs="tcp:6649:18"/> ſhal you do, where we haue no auto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity we do it not, but where we haue authoritie, we leaue it not vndone, There be many pagans among vs, that haue theſe abhommacions within their poſſeſſions, what ſhall wee goe and breake them? No, lette vs remooue them fyrſt out of their hartes, and when they bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Chriſtians, they will eyther deſire vs to breake them, or preuent vs, in breaking them themſelues, And in the ende of that Sermon, he ſayth: Wee preache agaynſte I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doles and Images, wee plucke them foorth of mens heartes, wee are the perſecutoures of Idoles, we confeſſe it: What are wee, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruers of Idoles, in deede I brake them not where wee cannot, I doe it not where the Owner of the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion complayneth, but where the Owner will haue it done, I doe it with thankes, and if I ſhall not doe it I am guiltie.</p>
            <p>Thus far <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> who is ſo far
<pb facs="tcp:6649:18"/> from bearing with imagery that he profeſſeth him ſelfe a ſharpe perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutour of Imagerye howe ſkyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullye, and howe trulye yea how wyſelye thys place of <hi>Auguſtine</hi> was aleaged, for defence of the Roodeloft iudge you, except the aleagers wyll affyrme this rood lofte to bee exempted from the Prynces iuriſdictyon, that hath accordyng to the wordes of God commaunded the ouerthrowe of all ſuche monumentes. Nowe becauſe I haue <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in myne handes and that openlye in the Churche, and manye of you preſent, it was boldelye and raſhlye ſayde,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.</note> that there was as muche dyfference bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Sacramentes of cyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſition, and baptiſme, as between a newe coate and an olde.<note place="margin">Collo. 2.</note> Saint <hi>Paule</hi> teachynge vs that they are bothe one,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.</note> I wyll reade vnto you the Iudgementte of Saint <hi>Auſtine</hi> touchyng thys
<pb facs="tcp:6649:19"/> matter,<note place="margin">Tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c. 26.</note> vppon the ſixte of S. Iohn, <hi>Sacramenta illae fuerunt in ſignis diuerſa, Sed in re ſignificata pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a ſunt: <hi>Theſe Sacramentes in ſignes differed from oures, but in the thing ſignifyed, they are like, and all one,</hi>
               </hi> and to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, in that place hee alleageth the Apoſtle Saynte Paule, and further,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.</note> 
               <hi>ad Quodvult deum,</hi> this <hi>Augustine</hi> who is pretented to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe Images doe recken them for Heretiques that pretende the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblynge or repreſentynge of GOD by an Image, and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them <hi>Antropomorphets,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Antedecor.</note> ſo doeth <hi>Origine</hi> vppon the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maynes,</hi> ſo doeth alſo <hi>Epipha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> the Biſhoppe of Cipris, who as hee wente towarde <hi>Bethell</hi> to meete with the Biſhoppe of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> paſſing by a Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage called <hi>Anablatha,</hi> hee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered an Oratorye or houſe of prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and ſayth hee: <hi>inueni velum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendens
<pb facs="tcp:6649:19"/> in foribus eiuſdem Eccleſiae, tinctum at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> depictum, et habens ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genem quaſi Christi, vel ſancti cuiuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, non enim ſatis memini cuius Jmago fuerit: cum hoc vidiſsem in Eccleſia Christi, contra authorita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem Scripturaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hominis pendere ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginem. ſcidi. &amp;c. <hi>I founde a cloth hanging in the enteraunce of the Churche, ſtayned and paynted, hauinge the Image, as it were of Chriſte, or of ſome other Saynte, I doe not well remember vvhoſe Image it vvas, vvhen I ſawe the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of a manne hang in the Churche of Chriſte, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye to the aucthoritye of the Scriptures, I cutte it downe. &amp;c.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus you alſo ſee the Scriptures by <hi>Augustine,</hi> by <hi>Origine,</hi> and <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyedde agaynſte Chriſtiannes, for the hauing of Images, yea ſo farre, that by thoſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
<pb facs="tcp:6649:20"/> they condemne images, mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in religion for Heretikes: but now between <hi>Jdolum, Simulachrum, Similitudinem,</hi> or <hi>Jmaginem,</hi> there is great difference, for <hi>Idolnus</hi> and <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulacrum,</hi> do euer ſignify the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols &amp; falſe Gods of the Gentiles, and are not to be applied vnto the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages of Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, this is as ſkil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and learned diſtinction as the reſt,<note place="margin">Tert. de Idol.</note> and of like truth. <hi>Tertullian</hi> in his booke againſt Idolatry deriueth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> from his Greeke primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>quod grece formam ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat ab eo per dimunitionem,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>deductum, ae<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> apud nos formulam fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit, igitur omnis forma, vel formula i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolum ſe dici expoſcit, <hi>That in greeke doth ſignifie a forme, or faſhion, for idole by diminutio is brought and doeth with vs indifferentlye ſignifie a ſhape or faſhion, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore euery ſhape or forme requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the name of Idole.</hi>
               </hi> Loe here is the difference of <hi>Jdolu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> as a greeke word <hi>et Similitudo</hi> or <hi>Imago</hi> a Latin
<pb facs="tcp:6649:20"/> word, ſignifying the ſelf &amp; the ſame thing, for <hi>Simulacru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> a Grammer Boye hauing learned the ſeconde parte of Grammer, can tel you that <hi>ſimilitudo</hi> commeth from <hi>ſimiles</hi> that ſignifieth like, ſo doeth <hi>ſimulacrum</hi> come from <hi>ſimulatum,</hi> that ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to liken, ſo <hi>ſimulacrum</hi> and <hi>ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litudo</hi> are both one, and ſignifieth a likeneſſe or Image, as <hi>imago:</hi> Loe here is their great learning that ſo boldlye and raſhly talke they know not what, thus muche for the thyrde branche.</p>
            <p>They ſay this Roodelofte is no monument of Idolatrie,<note place="margin">Tert de Idola<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Tertullian</hi> telleth vs, that <hi>monumentum</hi> is anye thing that putteth in minde the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of thinges not preſent. Nowe enter into the conſideration of your owne myndes, and remember with youre ſelues, whether when you beholde this lofte, you at ſome time or other, thinke with youre ſelues, ſometime yonder ſtoode a Crucifixe, Mary and Iohn, or when
<pb facs="tcp:6649:21"/> your Chyldren doe aſke you what this Lofte is, or why it ſtandeth there, and is more gaye, then the reſidue of the Churche: Doe you not aunſwere, It was the Roode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lofte, there ſtoode the Roode, Mary and Iohn, and when they ſaye fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, where is now the Roodes, and why is it now taken awaye, do you not aunſwere, They were Idoles, and therefore are taken away.</p>
            <p>Thus both the iudgemente of <hi>Tertullian,</hi> yea of all learned men, the cogitation of your own mindes, the queſtioning of your young ones, the common name whereby it is called, teacheth that it is a Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente of Idolatrie. Further the Lawes of this Realme, the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente of our moſt gratious prince, (whom the Almighty euer preſerue to the vtter ouerthrowe of Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie) with the practiſe of her Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners giuen vnto diuerſe lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned menne of this Realme, as well in the common Lawes, and ciuile
<pb facs="tcp:6649:21"/> Lawes, as in Diuinitie, teacheth vs that this Roodelofte is a monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente of Idolatrie, for euery where in the fyrſte yeare of her Gracious reigne, they gaue commaundement to ouerthrowe them in euery place, as may appeare vnto you by Saint Neots your next neighbour, where Doctor <hi>Benta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> &amp; Doctor <hi>Neueſon,</hi> and Sergent Fleetwood cauſed the Roodlofte there to be cut downe, by the ſeates of the quyer, leuing no memoryal thereof, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their doyng myght be an example vnto the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidue of the countrey to do the like. Seing therefore that theſe proofes do ſo clearelye declare it to bee a monumente of Idolatry, whyche in trueth hath and doeth greatlye offende the conſciences of the beſte ſorte, and diſquieteth the whole number of this congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Let me ſay vnto you as <hi>Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> at the red Sea ſayde to the <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elits,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 14.</note> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Pharao</hi> had he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>med the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in
<pb facs="tcp:6649:22"/> with his armye, feare ye not, ſtande ſtill, and beholde the great workes of the Lorde, ye ſee the Egiptians now, but after this day ſhall yee-ſee them no more, be not offended, quiet your myndes, ye nowe ſee this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that hath ſo troubled vs, but after this, in this fourme and faſhio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall ye ſee it no more, the Lord will ſo deale with vs, aſſure your ſelues, And thus muche for the fourthe branche.</p>
            <p>Now what learning, wiſedome, and gouernmente thoſe men haue, that take vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> defence, that I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages were not by the Papiſtes, brought into the Church to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped. That the commaundement doth not forbid the making and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of Images in religion, but the worſhip only, that there is ſuch dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ftrence in ſignification, betweene <hi>idolum, ſimulachrum &amp; imaginem,</hi> or <hi>ſimilitudinem,</hi> that one maye not bee put for an other, and the ſcriptures reprouing the Idolatrie of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then,
<pb facs="tcp:6649:22"/> may not be applyed againſt the images of Chriſtians: finallye that this Roodloft is no monument of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrie, by theſe things alredy ſaid you may eaſily perceiue, what lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſoeuer your Miniſter hath, truſt me they haue no learning wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, diſcretion, nor gouernment at all, lette them therefore deceiue you no more, for as in theſe things, ſo in other thinges belonging to religion ſhall you fynde them. There bee the bookes that they themſelues preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, take them who will, carry them whether you will, and if I haue not dealt ſimply, playnely, and truelye, then beleeue me no more, but if you finde this ſaying true, then quyet your ſelues, &amp; receiue the Doctrine and doubte thereof no longer. But ſome will ſaye this is verye hote, and vncharytable, ſo openlye, and ſo ſharpelye to reprooue, it woulde haue bene more mylde, and priuate: GOD is my wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe I wiſh no mannes fynger to
<pb facs="tcp:6649:23"/> ake, but onelye in the feare of God reprooue not the perſons, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue and conuince the Errors, that the mayntayners thereof maye be aſhamed of them, and leaue them, the ſimple warned to open theyre eares, to the hearing of anye ſuche thinges hereafter. S. Paule vnto the Galathians wiſheth ſuche as troubled the Congregation to bee cutte off from them.<note place="margin">Galat.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Phil. 3.</note> To the Phil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lippians he calleth them Dogges that maintained ſuperſtition after the receiuing of the goſpell. To the Corinthians,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.</note> he will not call them men that at Epheſus impugned his doctrine, but cals the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beaſtes. Chriſt calleth ſuch, wolues. In the reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Sainte Iohn,<note place="margin">Apoc. 9. 2. Pet. 2.</note> ſuche bee cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Locuſtes. Saint Peter calleth them beaſtes without reaſon, which the mild ſpirite of God compareth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enimies of his truth vnto,<note place="margin">Nahum. 2. Dan. 9.10. Mich. 4.</note> in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hum, Daniel, Miche as &amp; in other of the Prophets: who will reade ſhall perceiue. Chriſt our Sauiour, the
<pb facs="tcp:6649:23"/> mildeſt of all others calleth them Wolues, theeues, and murtherers<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Iohn Baſttiſt calleth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the broode of adders.<note place="margin">Mat. 3.</note> Such therfore as miſlike of the vpholding and maynteinance of errors in the ſighte of God,<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.</note> that hee by his Miniſters doth with all ſharpeneſſe ryſe vp agaynſte them, giuing them greate charge, that when the Wolfe aſſayleth the Sheepeful<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Mat. 10.</note> that then they do ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly oppoſe and ſette themſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt ſuch Wolues, yea euen vnto the loſſe of their lyues<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for if they be colde in ſuch aſſaultes, and preferre the benefite of their temporall qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etneſſe &amp; ſafetie,<note place="margin">Eze. 34.</note> before the glorye of God, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſafety of the ſoules co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto their charge, they ſhall loſe theirs owne liues in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world to come, and the blood of the ſimple that ſo peryſhe throughe theyr coldeneſſe, will GOD in the rygour of hys Iuſtyce, requyre at theyr hande, the LORD therefore graunte vnto the miniſters of hys Goſpell
<pb facs="tcp:6649:24"/> ſuche aſſiſtaunce of his holy ſpirite, that with all knowledge, zeale, and boldneſſe, they may diligentlye ſet foorth vnto his people, the truth of his worde, and with all conſtancy to withſtand and conuince the gaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayers thereof, to the aduancing of his own glory, the euerlaſting com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of his choſen, the downfall &amp; ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine of Antichriſt, whome the Lord Ieſus with the glorious preſence of his ſpedy comming, confound &amp; vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly ouerthrowe, vnto whom with God the father &amp; the holy Ghoſt, one eternall and euerlaſting God be all glory power &amp; dominion both nowe and euer.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:6649:24"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
